<article xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5'>
  <info>
    <title>Moonfire Games' Writing Toolkit</title>
  </info>

  <para>
    The Moonfire Games' Writing Toolkit (mfgames-writing) is a
    collection of small, relatively specialized utilities for
    converting, analyzing, and processing various file formats that
    are useful in the process of short-story and novel writing. The
    bulk of the program's functionality is centered around the DocBook
    5 XML format as a general purpose file format that is easily
    converted into other, more specific formats. The other utilities
    work at converting file formats into and from DocBook 5.
  </para>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Introduction</title>
    </info>

    <para>
      The intended use of these utilities are to allow an author to
      use a relatively simple file format, such as Creole or Markdown,
      to create the bulk of the writing. This allows them to use a
      variety of applications, such as Emacs, Notepad++, or any other
      text-based editor, without worrying about the formatting or
      layout. Then, using these utilities, the writer can convert the
      files into DocBook and either use that as an interim conversion
      format or to perform various analysis on the resulting file.
    </para>

    <para>
      Using DocBook as an interim format, stories can be formatted for
      posting on various websites or forums that have different
      posting guidelines such as BBCode or pure text. Controls for
      word-wrapping and section breaks simplifies the process of
      distributing stories and novels.
    </para>

    <para>
      These utilities can also be used to convert DocBook into
      Wiki-based (Creole for example) markup for automated updating of
      websites or to produce an online version of a story or
      author. With novels, longer pieces can be <quote>chunked</quote>
      so each chapter appears on a different page with links between
      them.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>DocBook</title>
    </info>

    <para>
      The system uses DocBook 5 as a common format for producing
      stories and novels. There are already well-known transformers
      for converting DocBook into ePUB, HTML, PDF, and a variety of
      other formats. However, the additional tags and requirement for
      XML correctness makes it difficult to edit DocBook directly
      without the use of a dedicated editor.
    </para>

    <para>
      All of the DocBook analysis and conversion use
      the <command>mfgames-docbook</command> script. The first
      parameter of the script determine the function. For example, to
      convert DocBook into BBCode uses <command>mfgames-docbook
      bbcode</command>.
    </para>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Conversion</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	The following formats
      </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Creole</title>
    </info>
  </section>
</article>
